是, 大臣  第3季第7集
THE LAST FANTASY | TLF HALFCD TeaM
压制：beiming6@TLF  字幕：破烂熊
仅供交流  严禁商用
-=破烂熊字幕组=-
翻译:tpring 校对:英吉沙 tpring
劫贫济富
(阿斯顿浪子队 0) (安卡索联队 2)
去会议室喝一杯 吉姆?     谢谢
Coming for a drink in the board room? Thanks.
趁足球俱乐部还在 好好享受吧
Ah, well, better enjoy it while the club's still here.
我们一向能撑过去的     这次不一样
We've always survived. it抯 different this time.
告诉他吧 布赖恩
Tell him, Brian.
昨晚我们和财政委员会紧急会面
We've had a meeting of the finance committee.
阿斯顿浪子队得算总帐了
Aston Wanderers will have to call in the Receiver!
你是说破产?     终场哨响了
You mean bankrupt? The final whistle.
就缺150万磅 吉姆
We need one-and-a-half million quid, Jim.
政府半分钟就浪费这么多
The government waste that every 30 seconds!
这什么话      知道大家怎么说吗 吉姆?
Oh, I say! You know what people are saying?
把地区议员捧成内阁大臣不合算
It's no good having a Cabinet Minister for an MP.
还不如留他在地方上 照顾选区
Better a local lad with time for his constituency.
胡扯     怎么?
That's absurd! Why?
议员进了内阁 好处多得很
There are advantages if an MP's in the Cabinet.
我们可没看到 是吧哈里
We haven't noticed them, have we, Harry
比如?      比如反映选区的民愿
Such as? It reflects well on the constituency.
结交有权有势的朋友
It's good to have powerful friends,
从高层施加影响 解危救难...
Influence in high places, a friend in need...
听着 朋友 现在需要150万磅救命钱
Listen, friend, what we need Is one-and-a-half million quid!
你愿不愿意施加一下影响?
So will you use that influence to help us?
这个...我是说抽象的影响
Well, when I said influence, I meant the indefinable sort,
无形的 潜在的优势
the intangible, subtle benefit
在大政方针的初级阶段
of an input into broad general policy at its early stages
朝有利选区的方向引导
while keeping constituency interests in mind.
就是不行?
Do you mean no?
这个...我大体愿意从根本上
Well, anything I can do in a broad,
以它为目标 我当然会...
general sense to further the cause, I will certainly...
出力
er, do.
如果我能的话 可是要一名大臣拨150万磅
If I can. But for a minister to pump one-and-a-half million
支援他选区的足球队
into his local football club!
他说不行
He means no.
能拉选票啊 争取年轻人 你会成为选区的英雄
But there'd be lots of votes in it. You'd be the hero.
"吉姆·哈克 阿斯顿队的救星" 终生保留议席
"The man who saved Aston Wanderers" Safe seat for life!
媒体会大做文章 反对党也会 法官也会
That might occur to the press. And the opposition. And the judge!
吉姆 这支队伍垮了 损失可惨重了
If this club goes to the wall It'll be a disaster.
看看我们的战绩
Look at our history!
英格兰足总杯 足联冠军 首次打入欧洲
FA Cup winners, League Champions, first team into Europe.
我都知道 哈里 可是话说回来
I know all that, but be fair.
这是地方事务 扯不上我们部
It's a local matter, not a ministerial one.
布赖恩 你是文艺休闲委员会主席 你没办法吗?
As chair of the Arts and Leisure Committee, can you help?
我? 别逗了
Me? You're joking.
我花了半年争取711磅
I spent half of yesterday trying to raise 711 quid
维修粮站美术馆的烟囱
to repoint the chimney on the art gallery.
那家破美术馆? 让它垮了得了
That miserable place? Why not let it fall down?
我倒没意见 不过万一砸到人 委员会要负责
I'd love to, but if it fell on somebody, the Council抯 liable.
那破地方归我们管
We own the bloody place!
不停有人出价要买
And we keep getting offers for the site.
上个月一家旧货市场刚找过我们
Save fair Supermarkets were after it last month.
等等 他们出多少?
Hold on, how much were they offering?
好像是200万磅
About two million quid, I think.
那你卖掉美术馆 球队就保住了
If you sold the art gallery, you could save the football club.
规划署要质询的     能看看美术馆吗?
There'd have to be a planning enquiry. Can we see it?
赶快去 他们5点下班
We'll have to be quick. They close at five.
还真破啊      2级保护建筑嘛
Hideous, isn't it? it抯 a Grade II listed building.
伯纳 我们的政治领袖大人
Bernard, what is our political master up to
对粮站美术馆打什么主意?
with the Corn Exchange Art Gallery
哦 您怎么知道?     反正不是听你说的 伯纳
Oh, how did you find out about that? Not from you, Bernard.
这个疏漏你要解释一下吗?
An omission you may care to explain.
这当然只是选区事务吧?     当然不是
Surely it抯 just a constituency matter? Surely not.
关闭美术馆 卖给旧货市场
Selling the gallery to Save fair Supermarkets
价款无息贷给阿斯顿足球队
and giving an interest-free loan to Aston Wanderers,
这是他作为议员而非大臣做的决定
he's acting as an MP not a minister.
这是原则问题 伯纳
It is the principle, Bernard.
你想不到后果会怎样吗?
Have you thought what the effect would be if this happens?
他会急速窜红     正是
He'd be very popular. Exactly!
红的发黑 红的可怕 然后呢?
Distressingly popular. Hideously popular. And then?
大臣下届会连任      这不是我们的首要目标
The minister would be re-elected. And that is not our top priority.
对我们部来说 谁当大臣无足轻重
in this department, it makes little difference who the minister is.
问题在于 要是别的球队也闹财政危机呢?
But the point is, suppose other football clubs got into difficulties?
赛犬会呢?
And what about greyhound racing?
补助了足球队 狗是不是也有份呢?
Should dog tracks be subsidised as well as football clubs?
人们想要的话 怎么不行?     伯纳
Why not, if that's what the people want? Bernard...
补助金...
subsidy...
是给艺术 给文化的
Is for art, for culture.
不是为了人们想要的东西
It is not to be given to what the people want!
是为了人们不想要 又非得有的东西
It is for what the people don抰 want but ought to have!
他们想要什么 自己会出钱的
If they want something they'll pay for it themselves!
不 我们补助的是教化 修养 精神文明提升
No, we subsidise education, enlightenment, spiritual uplift.
不是普通人的庸俗娱乐
Not the vulgar pastimes of ordinary people.
如此歪风 万不可长 必须制止
It's the thin end of the wedge. It must be stopped!
啊 大臣     汉弗莱 又怎么啦?
Ah, Minister. Humphrey. What's the matter now
大臣 预先提醒您一下
Minister, I thought you'd like early warning
内阁近期要重组
that there's a reshuffle in the offing.
该不是说...你不是...     不不 大臣
You don't mean... You're not suggesting... No, no, no, Minister.
这回是部门权责再分配
There is to be a departmental reorganisation.
是真的重组
A real reshuffle.
我们可能会增加职责呢      有好处么?
We may get extra responsibilities. Do we want them?
增加职责总是有好处的 大臣
We want all responsibilities, Minister,
如果同时增加人手和预算的话
If they mean extra staff and bigger budgets.
正是我们职责的广泛
It's the breadth of our responsibilities
让我们有分量 让您有分量 大臣
that makes us important, makes you important.
当您看到高楼大厦 人才济济
When you see vast buildings, huge staff
巨额预算 您看出什么?
and massive budgets, what do you conclude?
官僚主义?
Bureaucracy?
不 大臣 应该看到在这一切顶峰
No, Minister, you conclude that at the summit
高踞着一位伟大尊贵之人
there are men of great stature and dignity
君临天下 指点江山
who hold the world in their hands
所到之处莫不俯首称臣
and tread the earth like princes.
对 我能看到
Yes, I see.
所以新的职责要尽量攫取
So each new responsibility must be seized eagerly
而旧的职责要严加保卫
and each old one guarded jealously.
当然都是为您好 大臣
Entirely in your interests, of course, Minister.
是哦 谢谢你提醒我 汉弗莱
Thank you for warning me, Humphrey.
谢谢 大臣
Thank you, Minister.
哦 对了...
Oh! By the way...
关于粮站美术馆的提案
About the Corn Exchange Art Gallery proposal.
怎么?
What about it?
当然 那计划很有想象力 创意十足
It's the most imaginative scheme, novel idea,
但我觉得是否不大明智?
but I wonder if it might not be a little unwise?
为什么?
Why?
一座贵重的居民福利设施      一座怪物
A valuable civic amenity. A monstrosity!
一座贵重的居民福利怪物
A valuable civic monstrosity.
可它藏有一批英国美术珍品
An important collection of British paintings.
一点也不珍贵
Utterly unimportant.
18世纪二流肖像 19世纪三流风景画
Second-rate portraits, third-rate landscapes,
那些现代作品 泰特美术馆都不屑于收
modern paintings the Tate wouldn't even store.
可这是对非珍品的珍贵收藏
an important collection of unimportant paintings.
能大大提升过往居民的品味
And a source of great spiritual uplift to passing citizenry.
他们从不进去      可他们知道它在那
They never go in! But they know it抯 there.
馆长说平均每天只有11人参观
The curator says they average 11 visitors a day!
再说这是选区事务 无关政府 你操什么心?
It's a constituency matter. What's your interest?
这是原则问题     原则?
A question of principle. Principle?
您跟我说搞政治就是为了原则
What you used to tell me politics was about.
什么原则?
What principle?
从原则上允许剥夺艺术经费
The principle of taking money away from the arts
拿来支援足球这种东西
and putting it into football.
足球俱乐部属于商业机构
A football club Is a commercial operation.
就算它缺钱 也没理由发补贴
There's no cause for subsidy if it runs out of money.
怎么没有?     怎么没有?
Why not? Why not?
对啊 补贴艺术跟补贴足球都一样
Yes. There's no difference between subsidising football and art.
除了群众更喜欢足球一些
Except more people are interested in football.
我们的文化遗产必须保护
Our cultural heritage has to be preserved.
为了谁?
For whom?
为你们这些人 中产阶级知识分子
For people like you, you mean, the educated middle classes.
凭什么大家贴钱让少数中产阶级享乐?
Why should others subsidise the pleasures of the middle-class few
戏剧 歌剧 芭蕾
Theatre, opera, ballet!
补贴艺术是中产阶级劫贫济富之举
Subsidising art Is a middle-class rip-off.
大臣 您怎么能这么说?
Oh, Minister, how can you say such a thing?
补贴的目的在于教育
Subsidy is about education,
保护我们文明的精华
preserving the pinnacles of our civilisation.
您没发现吗?
Or hadn抰 you noticed?
不用你教我 汉弗莱 我也相信教育
Don't patronise me. I believe in education.
提醒你 我是伦敦政经学院毕业的
I'm a graduate of the London School of Economics, remember.
很高兴知道伦敦政经学院也不完全反对教育
Glad to learn even the LSE Is not opposed to education.
补贴体育没什么不妥 体育也是教育
Nothing wrong with subsidising sport. Sport is educational.
我们还有性教育 性也要补贴吗?
We have sex education too. Should we subsidise sex?
可以吗?
Could we?
让我们根据公众需要来发补贴
Let us choose what we subsidise by the extent of popular demand.
这没有错 这是民主      可是大臣 这是导火索
It抯 democratic. it抯 the thin end of the wedge!
长此以往 皇家歌剧院
What would happen to the Royal Opera House,
我们文明的精粹会怎样呢?
the very summit of our cultural achievement?
很好 就说皇家歌剧院 他们演什么?
Very good case in point. What do they do?
莫扎特 瓦格纳 威尔第 普契尼
Mozart, Wagner, Verdi, Puccini.
德国和意大利文化 没我们什么事
Germans and Italians, not our culture.
何苦花钱补贴轴心国文化?
Why should we subsidise the culture of the Axis powers?
是我们的欧洲友邦 大臣
Our European partners, Minister!
皇家歌剧院有9500万磅
The Royal Opera House gets 9.5 million pounds
公共拨款 年年如此
of public money every year.
为了谁? 平民百姓买不起30磅的票
And for what? The public can't afford 30 seats
就算买得起 也买不到 票不够
and if it could there aren't enough of them.
观众大多是商业巨头
The audience consists of big business executives
团体包场的都是银行 石油公司
block-booked by the banks and oil companies
跨国公司 还有你这种人
and multinationals and people like you.
皇家歌剧院是精英阶层的乐园
The Royal Opera House Is the establishment at play.
凭什么让劳苦大众出钱供养
Why should the working man pay for the gentry
你们买得起票的绅士老爷?
who can perfectly well afford their own seats?
大臣 我真的震惊了 这是野蛮 粗鄙
Minister, I'm quite frankly appalled. This is savagery, barbarism.
女皇的大臣居然说出这种话
That a Minister of the Crown should say such things,
简直...我们的文明算没救了
It's the end of civilisation as we know it,
并且完全扭曲事实真相
as well as being a gross distortion of the truth.
扭曲?
Distortion?
没有政府补贴 艺术不能生存
Art cannot survive without public subsidy.
莎士比亚拿政府补贴吗?
Did Shakespeare get a subsidy?
电影呢? 电影既是艺术也是教育
And films? Films are art and educational.
精英阶层怎么不补贴它?
Why does the establishment Ignore their subsidy?
因为你这种人偏爱歌剧
Because people like you prefer opera.
应该补贴电影这种
We should subsidise relevant art
群众喜闻乐见的艺术形式
like films that the man in the street can enjoy.
正是 他们是商业化的
Precisely! They are commercial.
抱歉失陪 我得先走了
Now, excuse me, I have to go early.
我不能继续这场骇人听闻的谈话
I cannot continue with this appalling discussion.
你去哪?     不去哪
Where are you gong? Nowhere.
那对不起了 咱们今天得谈清楚
Well, I'm sorry. We must talk this through.
不行 我得赶紧换衣服
I can't. I have to dress.
换衣服? 你到底去哪?
Dress? Where are you gong?
既然您非要问 我去皇家歌剧院
Since you insist, I am gong to the Royal Opera House.
真的假的啊?
Are you really?
团体票对不对?
Gala night, is it?
没错 是您要问的     很多常任秘书都去吗?
Yes, it is, since you ask. Lots of Permanent Secretaries gong?
当然有一些
Some, no doubt.
那就快去吧     谢谢您
Off you go, then. Thank you.
别被我耽搁了 同事聚会嘛
I don抰 want to make you late for your works' outing!
没说错吧 今晚演什么?
That's what it is, isn抰 it? What's on tonight?
"漂泊的荷兰人"(德国歌剧)
The Flying Dutchman.
又是欧洲友邦文化
Another of our European partners!
金酒兑汤力水 伊安?     谢谢
G&T, Ian? Thanks.
两杯金汤力 谢谢 要大杯
Two G&Ts, please, large ones.
再来几个熏鲑鱼三明治
And some of those smoked salmon sandwiches you have.
非常感谢
Thank you very much.
最近大气候如何?     灰蒙蒙的是吗?
So, how's the environment? Bit smoky, isn抰 it?
你说我们部里啊 还是那么混乱
Oh, you mean my department? Chaos, as usual.
怎么 国务大臣想自己管事?
What, the Secretary of State Is trying to run it?
那我还能应付
I could cope with that.
有个新晋大臣在给他支招
One of the junior ministers Is trying to help him.
我的天 是谁?
Oh, Lord. Who?
吉斯·弗里曼 政务次官     老天 是他?
Giles Freeman, the Paril Sec. Oh, Lord, him?
管他的 你有什么事?
Anyhow, what do you want to talk about?
这次计划署质询
A planning enquiry.
一定要得出正确的结论
Important we get the right result.
你知道我的调查员都是独立的
My planning inspectors are absolutely independent.
那当然     不受外界压力
Absolutely. No undue influence.
不 我绝无此意
No, I wouldn't suggest it.
但是说到非正式指导方针...
But if it抯 a question of giving certain informal guidelines...
将调查置于正确角度      对 没错
Putting the enquiry into perspective. Yes, indeed.
对背景作出阐释 帮助人们
Explaining the background to facilitate
深刻理解事件状况及其后果
an appreciation of the issues and implications.
这就合情合理了     很好
That would be quite proper. Splendid.
非常感谢
Ah. Thank you very much.
给 非常感谢
Er, right. Thank you very much.
干杯
Cheers.
要我堵什么漏子?
So what do you want me to fix?
是关于西密德兰一家美术馆
It's an art gallery in the West Midlands.
2级保护建筑 准备拆除
Proposed demolition of a Grade II listed building.
保证没问题 乐意之至
I'm sure we can arrange that. Only too happy.
那就好
Splendid.
保护建筑我们见一个拆一个
We're knocking them down all over the place.
不 不 必须驳回这个提案
No, no, the proposal has to be rejected.
是吗? 为什么?
Really? Why?
如果通过 他们会拿收益
If it goes through, they'll use the proceeds
去拯救当地濒临破产的足球队
to save the local football club from bankruptcy.
汉弗莱     我知道
Humphrey... I know.
一旦你从原则上允许
If once you allow the principle of money
把艺术的钱给普罗大众
being taken from the arts and given to ordinary people...
拿去寻开心
to enjoy themselves!
我同意     会落得什么下场啊?
I agree. Where will it end?
就是
Exactly.
谁出的馊主意?     我家主公
Where did this appalling idea come from? My lord and master.
他对那些大老粗的事最热心
He's getting very het up over the sweaty masses.
怎么没阻止他? 你干吗去了?
Didn抰 you stop him? What were you thinking of?
不关我事 是他的选区
It's not me. It's his constituency.
似乎他上周六向一群议员提出
Apparently he put it to a group of councillors last Saturday
他们欢呼雀跃
and they jumped at it.
我就说周末不能放他们出去乱跑
I've always said we shouldn't let him out at weekends!
净惹麻烦 你知道后果会怎样吧?
He only causes trouble. You realise where this could lead?
今天卖一座美术馆 救一支足球队
Today a gallery goes to support the local football club,
明天就要拿皇家歌剧院基金去修温布利球场了
tomorrow the Opera grant goes to modernise Wembley
可不是 质询的事我就指望你了?
So I can trust you to keep an eye on the planning enquiry
这个 我不能影响调查员     当然不能
Well, I can't influence the inspector... 'Course not.
但我能找个早该升职的人负责
But I'll put someone on it who's overdue for promotion.
那好 你会跟他讲清楚吧?
Good. You'll give him a thorough briefing, won't you?
哦 我相信他能看到根本问题的
Oh, I'm sure he will see the real issue.
文明对抗野蛮
Civilisation versus barbarism.
我们不能拿艺术经费支援热门体育
We can't have arts money gong to popular sport.
这是纵容低级趣味
It's simply subsidising self-Indulgence.
正是
Exactly.
大臣 安排您今天的日程之前
Minister, before we go over today's diary,
容我大胆提个建议
there's something I'd like to suggest, if I may be so bold.
尽管大胆说      恕我直言 私以为
Be as bold as you like. Well, I feel, and I say this with respect,
您不该过多插手足球队的事
you shouldn't get too involved with this football club affair.
果然大胆啊 这是我的选区事务
That is bold, isn抰 it? It's a constituency matter.
我大胆总比您撞个头破血流好 大臣
Better for me to be "bold" than you to be stumped, Minister!
很好笑
Very droll.
政府中有条惯例 别说大臣 即使是议员
It's axiomatic in Whitehall that even an MP, let alone a minister,
也不能干涉自己选区的规划事宜
should never take part in planning his constituency.
为什么?    由于地区事务的微妙平衡
Why not? Because of finely-balanced local issues.
您讨好多少选民就得罪多少 横竖不划算
You'll offend as many constituents as you'll please.
扯上公营机构更是险上加险
It's especially dangerous if there's a quango in the wings.
不 这回没什么好平衡的 大家都一边倒
No. Issues aren't finely-balanced. Everyone's on the same side,
极个别多愁善感 高高在上的文艺分子除外
except a few wet, long-haired scruffy art lovers!
请看您今天上午的安排 大臣
We'll take a look at your diary for this morning.
哦 好
Oh, fine.
10:15 文艺理事会秘书长 最大的公营机构
10.15, Secretary General of the Arts Council
10:45 文物古迹协会 11:00 国民托管组织
10.45, Historic Monuments Association, 11.00, The National Trust.
11:15 自耕农协会
11.15, Country Landowners Association,
11:30 英格兰乡村保护理事会
11.30, Council for Protection of Rural England...
英格兰乡村?     咱们乡村还挺多的
Rural England? There's quite a lot of it out there!
这些人找我有什么事?
Why are all these people coming to see me?
美术馆的事 大臣
The art gallery, Minister.
这是文艺建筑帮的
It's the arts and architecture mafia.
11:45 民间手工与民俗理事会
11.45, the Country Crafts and Folklore Council.
这又是谁?
Who are they?
麻绳帮
The raffia mafia.
有名望的手艺人
Influential people coming out of the woodwork.
泰晤士报会刊登他们的信
There'll be letters in The Times,
周末版会撰文批判您破坏文物
hostile articles in the Sundays, you'll be called a vandal.
他们会组织您选区选民展开对抗
They'll orchestrate opposition in your constituency.
干吗排进我日程里?
Why did you put them in my diary
我又没要你安排 你想什么呢 伯纳?
I didn抰 ask you to. What were you thinking?
我想的是汉弗莱爵士 大臣 他让我安排的
I was thinking of Sir Humphrey. He asked me to.
不不 这条妙计我支持定了 尽管放马过来
I'm gong to support this excellent scheme, come what may.
随便您 大臣 能不能先请您过目
As you will. May I just have your approval for
这份地方政府津贴修正案?
this local government allowances amendment?
什么?      这是下院提交的法令草案
It's a statutory instrument to go before the House.
作为地方政府管理大臣
As Minister for Local Government,
您必须批准对1971年2号条例
you need to authorise that revised paragraph 5,
第5条的修订于3月18日起生效
Number 2 regulation 1971 shall come into operation on March 18th,
同时撤销地方政府津贴修正案
revoking regulation 7 of the local government
1954(乙)条例第7条
allowances amendment regulations 1954b.
这都什么意思?
What the hell's all that mean?
里面有份摘要 大臣
There is an explanatory note.
"以上条例旨在规范"
"These regulations make provision
"地方政府成员津贴的依法支付问题"
for allowances to members of local authorities.
"简要说明 1971年地方政府"
Explanatory note, regulation 3
"津贴修正案第2条例"
of the local government allowances amendment 1971,
"即1971年条例"
the 1971 regulations,
"作为新条例 取代了1954年条例第3条"
substituted regulation 3 of the 1954 regulations.
"1972年地方政府津贴修正案第3条"
3 of local allowances amendment regulations 1972,
"即1972条例 进一步"
the 1972 regulations, further made
"修正了1954条例第3条"
amends regulation 3 of the 1954 regulations
"增加了会议津贴"
by increasing the maximum rates of attendance
"和经济损失补助最高限额"
and financial loss allowances."
我一点也没...     "1982年第7条例"
I haven't the faintest... "Regulation 7, 1982,
"撤销了1971条例第3和第5条"
revoked both regulations 3 and 5 of the 1971 regulations,
"其中第5条是对先前失效条例的废除"
regulation 5 being revoking earlier spent regulations,
"次年4月1日起生效"
with effect from 1st April next.
"为了保留1971条例的第3和第5条"
preserve regulations 3 and 5 of the 1971 regulations
"上述条例撤销了1972条例第7条"
by revoking regulation 7 of the 1972 regulations."
这是摘要吗?
That's an explanatory note?
是啊 我觉得很清楚
Yes, I think that's all quite clear.
为什么要我听这一团乱麻?
Why must I listen to this piddling gobbledegook?
抱歉大臣 我认为这个机会能确保
I thought it would be an opportune moment for you to ensure
在大臣您治理之下
that as a result of your ministerial efforts,
地方理事会成员能得到更多会议津贴
local councillors will get more for attending meetings.
哦 就是这个意思?     对
Oh, is that what it means? Yes.
好啊伯纳 你说得对 这是机会
Excellent. It is, as you say, opportune.
我能不能再提个小建议?
And may I make one further small suggestion?
随便提
Be my guest.
汉弗莱爵士昨晚会见了伊安惠沃爵士
Sir Humphrey had a word with Sir Ian Whitworth last night.
伊安惠沃     美术馆是登记在案的建筑
Ian Whitworth! The Corn Exchange is a listed building,
所以质询将由他手下一名调查员主持
so one of his planning inspectors will conduct the enquiry.
汉弗莱爵士和伊安爵士会给他非正式指导方针
Sir Humphrey and Sir Ian will give him some informal guidelines.
什么叫"非正式方针"?
How do you mean, "Informal guidelines"?
指导方针没什么不对 人人都有工作方针
Everyone has guidelines for their work.
规划调查员不是独立的吗?
I thought planning inspectors were impartial?
真的 大臣
Oh, really, Minister!
当然 火车也是独立的
So they are. Railway trains are impartial too.
只要铺好轨道 它们照样跟着走
But if you lay down the lines for them, that's the way they go!
可这不公平     这是政治 大臣
But that's not fair! it抯 politics, Minister.
汉弗莱爵士怎么搞起政治来了?
What has Sir Humphrey got to do with politics?
他是公务员 我负责政治
He's a civil servant. I'm the one in politics!
对 大臣 确实是您负责
Yes, Minister, indeed you are!
他们打算怎么对调查员施压?
How do they intend to put pressure on this planning inspector?
规划调查员有专门的等级制度
Planning inspectors have an independent hierarchy.
只要知道谁想升职就行
A vulnerable one Is one anxious for promotion.
怎么任命主持质询的调查员
How are planning inspectors chosen for an enquiry
大臣能干涉吗?
Could a minister interfere?
大臣都是我们的主公     很好
Ministers are our lords and masters. Good.
环保部政务次官
The Paril Sec at the Department of the Environment
是我的老朋友吉斯弗里曼
Is an old friend, Giles Freeman.
如果弗里曼先生能安排一名
Well, if Mr Freeman could arrange for an inspector
不在乎晋升的调查员
who didn抰 care about promotion,
比如说 找个快退休的
lf, for instance, he's about to retire,
他下结论时应该
he'll probably reach a verdict favouring
更为公众而非部门着想
the community rather than the department.
好 能帮我接吉斯的电话吗?
Good! Get me Giles on the phone, would you?
他的私人秘书说他今晚
His Private Secretary says he can meet you
投票之后在休息室等您
in the lobby after the vote this evening.
伯纳 你想过从政吗?
Bernard, have you ever thought of gong into politics?
我不想 大臣     为什么?
Oh, no, Minister. Why not?
我在我的字典里定义过政治     怎么定义的?
I once looked it up in my thesaurus. What did it say?
煽动 阴谋 操纵 推脱 贪赃枉法 蛊惑人心
Manipulation, intrigue, wire-pulling, evasion, graft, rabble-rousing...
还是留给诸位主公来操心好了
I'd prefer to leave that to our lords and masters.
我觉得我没有这些素质
I don't think I have the necessary qualities.
可别低估你自己 伯纳
Don't underestimate yourself, Bernard!
现在哈克拉拢到了吉斯弗里曼
Now it seems Hacker has got at Giles Freeman,
我们部的政务次官
the Parli Sec in my department,
他非要任命他的调查员 不要我那个
Appointing a different planning inspector to the one I chose
他的调查员赞成哈克的计划
One who'd be sympathetic to Hacker's scheme.
确实让人担心     担心? 这是死路一条
This is rather worrying. Worrying? it抯 desperate!
很可能这个规划调查员
There's now every danger that the planning inspector
会自己拿主意
could make up his own mind!
当地人会热烈欢迎这个计划
There's likely to be huge local support for the scheme.
我能帮什么忙?
But how can I help?
我指望你出主意呢 阿诺德
I hoped you'd have some ideas, Arnold.
等等 我想到了
Walt a minute! I've thought of something.
下周部门重组的时候
When the departmental reorganisation occurs next week...
你可以任命哈克为艺术总管大臣
you could make Hacker Cabinet Minister responsible for the arts!
他不是化外之民吗?     对
But isn抰 he a complete philistine? Yes.
反正工业部长也整天做无用功
But then the industry Secretary Is the idlest man in town.
教育部长没教养
The Education Secretary is illiterate!
就业部长该失业
The Employment Secretary Is unemployable!
这倒是 好主意 汉弗莱
Quite. That's good thinking, Humphrey.
哈克当了艺术总管大臣
Hacker can hardly start out as Cabinet Minister for the arts
不能首先就拆美术馆
by closing down an art gallery.
正是     但这不是内阁改组吧?
Exactly. But it抯 not a reshuffle, is it?
不 只是职能重新分配
No, I simply meant reorganise.
将艺术和广播电视
Move the arts and telecommunications
划入行政部管辖范围
into the purview of the DAA.
艺术和电视?
Arts and television together?
它俩有什么联系?
What have they got to do with each other?
死对头嘛
They're complete opposites.
不会造成一个霸王部门吧?
Wouldn抰 we be creating a monster department?
你们已经掌握地方政府了
You've already got local government as well.
艺术和地方政府天生一对
Arts and local government go well together.
怎么讲?
How so?
老乡骗老乡也是一门艺术
Well, the art of jiggery-pokery!
你确实是刚刚想到的吧?
You only just thought of this here and now, did you?
是啊 怎么?     你也是艺术家 对吗?
Yes, why? Bit of an artist yourself, aren't you?
哦 阿诺德
Oh, Arnold!
还有事吗 伯纳?     大臣 您会见足球队之前
Anything more, Bernard? Sir Humphrey wants a word
汉弗莱爵士有话要说
before your meeting about Aston Wanderers.
他不知道我不会动摇吗?
But I'm unshakeable on that!
没用的 汉弗莱 我决心已定
It's no good, Humphrey, my mind is made up.
尽管如此 大臣 内阁改组有新消息了
You might be interested in a new development
你说只是再分配的     不只是再分配
You said it was just a reorganisation. Not just a reorganisation.
而是再分配
A reorganisation.
我荣幸地宣布 它给我们部
I'm delighted to tell you that it has brought us,
给您增加了荣耀和分量
brought you, new honour and importance.
在现有的职责之上
In addition to existing responsibilities,
您又被任命为艺术总管大臣
you will be Cabinet Minister responsible for the arts.
是吗 这是好事啊
I say, that's rathergood, isn抰 it!
等等 你怎么比我还先知道?
Hold on, how do you know before I do?
内阁秘书作出决定之后
I just happened to be with the Cabinet Secretary
我刚好在他身边
shortly after the decision was taken.
这样啊
I see.
艺术总管大臣
Cabinet Minister with responsibility for the arts!
这样啊      可不是吗
Well, well, well! Yes, indeed.
好啊汉弗莱 还有事吗? 我有会要开
Anything more? I'm about to start a meeting.
对了 那个会
Oh, the meeting, yes.
大臣 我衷心希望您站在新角度
I do hope you've considered the implications
考虑此事的影响
of your new appointment on the subject.
拯救一支足球队?     不不
Rescuing a football club? No, no.
不知道别人会怎么看
I was wondering how it would look
您作为艺术总管大臣
If as Minister responsible for the arts,
上任头一件事就拆美术馆
your first act was to knock down an art gallery.
那美术馆其实不错的...
It's quite a decent little art gallery...
就是     建筑挺有意思
Exactly. Interesting building.
2级保护建筑     大臣 您该开会了
Grade II listed. Minister, your meeting...
天啊 我该怎么说?
Oh, my God! What am I gong to say?
威金森 诺博和格林议员      布赖恩 幸会
Councillors Wilkinson, Noble and Green. Brian, good to see you.
彼得 道格
Pete... Doug.
这是汉弗莱阿普比爵士 我的常任秘书
Sir Humphrey Appleby, my Permanent Secretary.
那他是临时秘书?
You mean he's only a temp!
形势一片大好 我们争取到了所有政党
It's gong great. We've got all the political parties with us
郡议会也支持
and the County Council.
只等你们部批准
All we need is your approval for using
把款项贷给足球队就行了
the sale of the art gallery as a loan to the club.
这个 恐怕有点问题
Well, I'm afraid there's a snag.
你说没问题的     呃 现在有了
You said there weren't any! Well, there is.
怎么?      问题在于...这个...
Well, it抯 just that... Well...
似乎...貌似...
It appears... Well, it seems...
应该说问题出现于...
Well, I should say it has emerged...
我想汉弗莱爵士比我清楚
Sir Humphrey can explain better than me.
做不到 先生们 那家美术馆是...合伙基金
It can't be done, gentlemen. Er, the art gallery is... it抯 a trust.
规定专款专用的      对 是合伙基金
Terms of the original bequest. Yes, it抯 a trust.
我们得拆别的建筑
We shall have to knock something else down!
学校 教堂 医院 肯定能腾出地来
School, church, hospital... There's bound to be something!
真不敢相信 你要我回去告诉大家
I can't believe this. So I have to tell people back home
说你出尔反尔?
you've gone back on your word?
是你自己的主意啊     不是我 是法律不允许
It was your own idea! it抯 not me, it抯 the law.
你早干吗去了 现在才发现?
Why didn抰 you find out till now
这个...
Well...
那我挑明了告诉你
Let me be absolutely frank with you.
实际上 这事有可能 仅仅是可能成功
It would be possible to push this through
不过要拖很久     拖呗 已经这么久了
but it would take an awful long time. Ok, we've spent enough.
问题在于 这就要放弃另一件事
Trouble is, something else would have to go by the board.
我手头正忙着的事
The thing that's taking my time at the moment
是要争取增加地方议员经费
Is forcing through councillors' expenses
和会议津贴
and attendance allowances.
我不能同时对两边施压
I can't put my personal weight behind both schemes.
那就放弃地方议员涨津贴的事
Forget about the increased allowances for councillors
专心解决卖美术馆的法律问题
and concentrate on the legal obstacles, the sale of the art gallery.
法律问题很难搞的      这回尤其难搞
Tricky things, legal obstacles. This is a particularly tricky one.
就算费尽心思 最后还可能功亏一篑
At the end of the day, you might still fall.
都没准的     如果这样的话...
Every possibility. If that's the way it is...
我们有可能计划
there's a chance we might want to close
年末关闭爱丁山小学
Edgehill primary at the end of the year...
那块地也能卖个一两百万
That site would fetch a couple of million, give or take.
好吧 就这么办 不会跟你过不去
Well, there it is, then. No ill feelings to you.
好的 那你回地方上解释
Good. And you'll explain locally
我们绕不过法律规定?
that we can't overcome the legal obstacles?
尽管放心 继续努力吧
'Course we will. Carry on with the good work!
大臣 您真是艺术家
Oh, Minister, a work of art.
恕我失陪 我要去换衣服了    又是工作聚会?
If you'll excuse me, I have to dress. Another works' outing?
呃 汉弗莱     大臣?
Er, Humphrey... Minister?
作为艺术总管大臣
As Cabinet Minister responsible for the arts...
我能一起去吗?
could I come too?
是 大臣
Yes, Minister!